Pravin Kumar

VP of Product Management, TriNet

ppk@kumarfamily.us

Summary

Experience Highlights

Product innovation leader with a unique blend of strategy, product management, and technical competence

Transformational executive - have turned around and transformed product organizations

Breadth of organizational experience – worked in enterprise and startups

Excellent communication - worked with investors, boards, industry and financial analysts

Negotiating skills – led complex multi-million-dollar deal negotiations

Management - consistently instilled a culture of collaboration, creativity and accountability

Career Highlights

Delivered successful products in Document Management, HR, CRM, AdTech, Supply Chain, and Procurement

Negotiated multi-million-dollar partnerships with global system integrators

Participated in raising over \$50M in venture funds for various startups

Managed large complex products with multiple product lines (e.g. platform w/ > \$1.6B revenue)

Managed outsourced and distributed product & engineering organizations

Experience

Board Member

June 2017 - Present

VP, Product Management at TriNet

October 2014 - Present

Board Member

July 2015 - February 2017 (1 year 8 months)

Principal Program Manager - Alliances & Strategy at Microsoft

April 2013 - October 2014 (1 year 7 months)

Lead alliances and partner strategy in the Dynamics CRM R&D team - work with strategic SI partners and ISVs to build an ecosystem for the rapidly growing Dynamics CRM business.

Sr. Director, Marketing Solutions at Microsoft

January 2012 - April 2013 (1 year 4 months)

Working with the largest brands to build innovative, compelling marketer solutions to help them connect with consumers. These solutions leverage the entire Microsoft portfolio of platforms and solutions.

Principal

August 2011 - January 2012 (6 months)

Product strategy consultant.

Senior Director Product Management at Yahoo!

September 2009 - August 2011 (2 years)

Managing the Product Management team for Yahoo's strategic advertising platform, Apt.

Principal

May 2009 - September 2009 (5 months)

Product strategy consulting.

VP, Products & Technology

June 2008 - May 2009 (1 year)

- · Led product management, UX, development, QA, and Infrastructure
- Built an outstanding team that delivered 2 releases of the new enterprise product in 6 months, increasing enterprise bookings by 75% YOY
- Worked with product marketing to re-position product
- Developed product and technology strategy for the leading sales prospecting application with over 25,000 users
- Instituted agile development processes across geographically diverse teams in 2 months
- Led the development of a new Web 2.0 technology platform based on Ruby on Rails, REST-based web-services and ESB (Enterprise Service Bus)

VP, Products at Ketera Technologies, Inc.

June 2004 - May 2008 (4 years)

Responsible for all aspects of product development and delivery for an on-demand enterprise application suite with over 75K users

- Developed product strategy and launched five new differentiated solutions into the marketplace over 4 years
- Managed a team of 90 developers, QA & product managers
- Instituted a product management process that increased transparency to sales and marketing while improving the accuracy and velocity of the development process
- Instituted a metrics-driven development process
- Positioned Ketera as an innovator in the marketplace

Sr. Director, Product Marketing

- Developed the first formal pricing model
- Conducted survey to develop product strategy and positioning

Director, Market Strategy at SAP

October 2001 - June 2004 (2 years 9 months)

Delivered product strategy and market requirements for the manufacturing vertical for SAP Business ByDesign – included a prioritized list of application features and functions based on revenue and penetration targets

• Responsible for market survey of manufacturing vertical for SAP Business ByDesign – conducted 56 interviews with CXOs in 9 countries.

Director, Product Marketing, Supply Chain Collaboration Products

- Managed a product line that generates \$100M+ a year in revenue
- Conceived and rolled-out Supply Chain Collaboration hub product
- A trusted advisor to the development team and worked closely with them on product requirements definition and delivery
- Recognized as an expert in Supply Chain Collaboration wrote journal articles, and presented at numerous conferences
- Established a strong relationship with field and developed sales kits, and positioning for SCC solutions

VP of Products

June 2000 - April 2001 (11 months)

Managed product management, development, and operations of an IT project marketplace

- Recruited a 45-person engineering team
- Implemented product management and engineering processes to deliver releases every 6 weeks
- Managed the transition from LISP to Java-based architecture
- Planned and executed a data-center transition from Boston to San Jose with zero impact to customers
- Worked with CEO to raise \$18 million in venture capital

VP of Engineering

June 1999 - June 2000 (1 year 1 month)

Hired as first employee and managed Engineering & Operations

Delivered first version in 10 weeks and was featured in Time magazine:

http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,31140,00.html

- Designed and led implementation of back-end supply-chain system, supplier portal, contentmanagement system
- Integrated supply chain system with Solomon GL & accounting system
- Deployed a redundant, high-performance architecture for a high-volume, consumer website

Setup management structures and development processes and delivered over
7 releases in the first year

Director, Engineering at CrossWorlds Software, Inc.

March 1998 - April 1999 (1 year 2 months)

Engineering Manager, Tools Group

- Lead the definition and development of initial Supply Chain Product
- Defined and lead the development of a visual BPM tool
- Gathered and prioritized customer requirements over multiple releases
- Led implementation of software development methodology for the engineering team

Director, Advanced Development at Manugistics, Inc.

June 1994 - March 1998 (3 years 10 months)

Engineering Manager, Advanced Engineering/UI Framework Groups

- Developed and executed Manugistics Advanced Engineering Strategy including transitioning to web-based UI
- Communicated Manugistics technology strategy to external parties: industry analysts, customers, partners
- Architected and led the development of a user interface framework that was used across entire product line

Engineering Manager, SAP Integrator

- Envisioned and delivered the first version of the Manugistics/SAP Integrator within nine months from conception to roll-out
- Led inter-company, cross-functional, product roll-out team that included marketing, business development and professional services

Team Lead, Foundation Module at Marcam Corporation

June 1993 - June 1994 (1 year 1 month)

Recruited and built a fourteen person development team that produced the reusable user-interface components and system level services for a large, clientserver, ERP application

• Planned and delivered four releases over a nine month period

Project Lead at Sun Microsystems, Inc.

March 1987 - June 1993 (6 years 4 months)

- Designed and implemented the user interface, and RPC components for AnswerBook, Sun's first commercial C++-based product
- Analyzed Organizer (graphical file-manager) performance and implemented performance enhancements, and bug fixes

Manager, Communication & Signal Processing Labs at University of Maryland, College Park

December 1984 - March 1987 (2 years 4 months)

- Designed and implemented image and speech processing library
- System administrator for a large, heterogeneous network of UNIX systems

Education

Harvard Business School Executive Education

Governing for Nonprofit Excellence, Business Administration and Management, General, 2017 - 2017 University of Maryland, College Park

BSEE, Electrical Engineering, September 1980 - May 1985

Honors and Awards

CODiE Awards Judge

Pravin Kumar

VP of Product Management, TriNet

ppk@kumarfamily.us



Contact Pravin on LinkedIn